personally thank you for uh this uh
practical uh live demo. Cool. Thanks Bob
and thanks everybody. Thank you Nick.
Well I think this is the perfect segue
because I mean everything has been
really practical in these sessions. This
is why we definitely have the best track
by the way. Um but jokes aside uh we are
looking forward to uh uh to this next
session which is going to be um
essentially talking about AI uh and uh
refactoring legacy code which is a huge
topic right now and we're going to be
inviting uh a Scott worish uh with over
40 years of experience um a real uh Java
uh champion and veteran
Uh so without further ado, let's get
into it.
[Music]
Hi Scott. Hey, how you doing? Yes. Good.
Good. How are you? I'm great.
Amazing. Well, um Oh, sorry. You were
about to say I I was just gonna say yes.
I I do have uh a lot of experience in
legacy code. So
yeah, I mean this is why this is why we
invited you. We're extremely keen to
hear and leverage your expertise uh on
this and so um because I know we all are
very interested and we have little time.
I'll just uh give the mic over to you.
All right. Excellent. Well, thank you
very much. So, um, yeah, if, uh, if you
want the slides, that's that's the link
to them. My name is Scott Reisham. I,
um, I have been working in in legacy
code for most of my career. Probably
y'all have, too. You just don't realize
it. Code that you wrote last week. It's
legacy code. Everybody's all excited
about what AI can do for generating new
code, but what can it do for legacy
code? So um the
uh you know I guess the most obvious
thing you can do for doing for for
legacy code is to
um basically take some code submit it to
a an AI tool and and ask it what's
what's wrong with this code? Um and so I
I submitted this to five different AI
tools. this uh this a very simple
contrived function here uh strings of
length five in uppercase. So it's going
to basically take a an array a list of
strings
uh get the string map them to uppercase
look for any that are five characters in
length and add each one to a result
return. So that's pretty pretty simple
straightforward. Um if you're an
experienced Java developer you'll
probably say you probably don't want to
use for each for that. there's better
ways to do it, but there are other
things in here that you may not have
caught that u we're going to see if the
AI catches. Okay, so um so the first
basically I'll make a list of all the
all the different AI tools that I use.
First, we got chatgpt
um and it noticed what I suggest about
the the for each and um and it suggested
we should use a collect operator instead
which is is proper uh Java idiomatic
code. It also suggested that if you call
two uppercase on a unicode
uh string that or characters that
sometimes that'll change it to be a two
character string. Uh yeah, two character
string instead of just a single
character. So that might throw off this
five character check. Um I don't know
how many of youall noticed that.
Um so it also suggested renaming the
function to be clear that you're doing
the check before you're doing the
conversion just so that people would
know. Um and it doesn't like the the
generalized input here. This uh import
Java util star. It suggests that you
should use the specific library is back
should use Java util list and Java util
array list so that uh there it's all
specified that's a tabs versus spaces
argument I don't want to have right now
but uh chat GPT has its opinion so since
I'm a Windows developer uh Windows user
I tried it on MS copilot because if
you're on Windows you just can't get
away from MS Copilot. Okay. Um, and so
it uh it found the the the Unicode
uppercase problem and said that it may
change the the string length. Um, and it
suggested that you do the filtering
before you do the mapping so that it
would be less confusing. So yeah, I
guess you you could do that too.
Um, so next we have Google Gemini and it
points out that you should use collect
rather than for each because that's the
proper idiomatic approach in Java
streams. It also points out that while
it's good to not have side effects in
code, some users might expect it based
on how the function was named. And then
uh
chatgpt generated this uh this outline.
So, and it was very proud to point out
that uh Google Gem Google Gemini did not
mention the two uppercase length issue
which chat GPT caught. So, a little bit
of a little bit of struting there. Um
then just for fun, I tried gro um and I
was pleasantly surprised. It it pointed
out that using for each isn't idiomatic
Java and we should use collect instead.
also caught the unic code problem
uh calling two
uppercase but it caught even more. It
pointed out that array lists are not
thread safe and so if we decide to
change this to instead of saying stream
using a parallel stream that it would
have undefined results. Um and and then
it noticed that we don't check for null
input and so that would throw an
exception and it should probably be
handled more
elegantly and then it provided the code
to do
that.
Um and then it uh generated expected
output for some sample code and showed
that it did in fact work and it
summarized its finding and offered to
rewrite the the code using all of the
suggestions that it had. That was that
was really pretty nice. And then since
Claude is sort of the uh the de facto
developer tool, um I tried it in Claude
and it's uh it pointed out that in some
cases uppercasing might change the
length of string to a a resultant string
so that we should do the filter before
doing the uppercasing. But it didn't
catch the for each operation being poor
Java style. Um it did give an
explanation of u you know this is a
potential output for a function and so
but it said that the the application was
correct as written. So, here's a table
showing the different things that that
each one caught. And you can see that uh
Grock is is our big winner here. And
Google Gemini um is was the weakest. But
every one of them has certain strengths
and
weaknesses. And I just what I take it
take away from this is that you should
not depend on chat GPT. I'm even using
the uh the pro version of chat GPT. And
so you should you should actually make
sure that you're you're comparing this
against uh yeah two or maybe even three
uh AI tools to to check your code.
Pretty interesting. Um now what if
you've got say a thousand lines of code?
No, I do not own a Tesla.
Uh, and so if you got, you know, a
couple thousand lines of code like like
I have, hundreds of thousands of line,
you you don't want to break it up into
15 line snippets, um, you know, like
like this to to try and have it go and
and regenerate it. What you want to do
is um you want to break it up into small
enough chunks that it'll fit in in the
uh the AI window. Um and yeah, basically
this is the uh the code that uh chat GPT
generated the code using all of these
suggestions from from everybody. Um but
yeah, if you if you have say more than a
hundred lines of code, then um that your
your results are not going to be quite
as good. But then again, it's sort of
like walking around your your office and
and asking somebody to evaluate the
code. If you give them 15 lines, uh
different people are going to find
different things real quickly. If you
give them a 100 lines, they're going to
glance at it and they may not find
things. Um, I might uppercase change the
strings length or have a unic code side
effects. Okay, so in in Unicode, there
are some strings. Actually, one of the
the AIS gave an example. If you use a
beta, it turns and you uppercase it, it
turns into an SS. I don't I don't know
the uh the specific character, but yeah.
Anyway, um
so with that in mind, I also thought,
well, what about debugging? Do we use AI
to debug? So, um you probably heard from
uh uh I'm sorry, I can't remember the
guy's name right now, but he he spoke
about Juny. And so, I I work alone. I
don't have any developers working with
me. I'm supporting a 20-year-old
application. Don't have any
documentation for it. and I was trying
to to debug something and or and trying
to test something and I couldn't get it
to generate the the right information.
So my problem is, you know, I'm this
method is keeps returning no and I don't
know why and I'm staring at it all, you
know, for 20 30 minutes trying to figure
it out. And I said, I'll just ask Juny.
Okay. So um what I did is this is the
prompt that I gave Juny. I said the
initialization that this object is not
working as I expected. Calling this
method on that object always returns a
null. How can I properly initialize the
data so that the function returns a
value? So it goes and it generates its
its results. So reviewed it gets the
structure of the code for the object
it's looking at. It opened this another
one of the Java files and looked at the
method that how that was in implemented
and initialized. opens another file u
makes sure that the constructor is
working as expected. Gets the structure
folks looks at the test data
initialization. Opens the test file. Saw
how it's tested. Saw the data output and
and how it was what was expected. Um it
opens a test. Looks at it some more.
Scrolls down a little bit. Says ah this
method doesn't um show this particular
issue in the test class. and we find out
h aha it doesn't my I have a fake object
that goes and overrides this uh this
table model and it does not initialize
it doesn't override the the get table
data item so basically I'm I'm missing
this override so I need to give it the
data that it needs to have um so this is
the issue I need to go and uh and extend
this this table model and I need to
override this class So pretty
interesting. Um, and then it uh it was
so helpful went and added this this uh
method to to my test class so that I I
can get it to work properly. Thought
that was pretty darn cool. I'd been
stuck on it for at least an hour staring
at the code and it it came up with this.
Um, so I'm keeping a close eye on it. Oh
man, I'm almost out of time. So there
are other tools out here. Um there's
Madern uh or open rewrite. Um and I
would strongly recommend you get into
that. Um there's also Kodto which you
it's a it's a plugin for Intelligj and
also for uh for uh VS Code. So it's a
really handy tool that does all some all
all really cool stuff. And then there's
another one that's uh that's nice called
Refac.ai. I like that each of them.
Thank you, Michael. That's exactly the
uh the example the AI caught.
Um Refact.ai is
uh is a a really handy tool. I like that
all of them have a free version because
as as you start using these tools and
you know 15 20 bucks a month for for
each tool, it starts to add up a while.
Um so I I am supposed to be wrapping up
right now.
Um, do we if we don't have any
questions, I've got more I can show you.
But, uh, let's see
here. The fake data loader class extends
that table model fails to override the
data table, which is likely an abstract
or critical method in the apparent,
right? Yeah, it the the data table data
loader table model. It's a swing
uh uh Java swing thing that you you
youngsters probably have never heard of.
Um, but it uh it's so that you can use a
a table like an Excel table and you can
access the data. And so I just I don't
want to have to use a UI in my test. So
I just did a fake override of that so it
wouldn't be going sending messages back
and forth to the UI. It would go and and
catch all those and handle it.
Um, if there are no other questions,
real quick, I want to show you uh
something that uh that we did. I work on
the approval test project and we had
this problem where it was building up
the uh the uh file paths in a way that
we didn't expect. And so we needed to go
through and refactor how it was doing
things. We created a new function that
would go and and and get us the file
path the way that we wanted, but it was
done in in about 20 30 different places
of the code. And it wasn't like a quick
uh uh you know find and replace type
function. It needed to kind of turn it
inside out to to make the function going
going right. And so I fired up. I said,
'You know why? Why don't we have Jeie so
we don't spend an hour going in here and
rewriting everything? And Jeie went
through and this took probably 10 almost
15 minutes to go through and look
throughout the entire project and it
made these changes. Then it gave us a
little report of all the changes that it
made. It uh you know took three lines
out and added three lines in. So
basically changed all these files. I
thought that was really cool. And then
we started looking through because we
were skeptical that you know some AI is
going to do stuff and took a look at the
code and um yeah it did do what what we
expected turned everything inside out um
the way we expected but then it also
went through and cleaned up things. So
we had this, you know, we're creating a
file name and then calling new file on
this file name. You're sticking the file
separator so you know whether it's
Windows or or Linux. And so it do that
correctly. Didn't even realize that
there's a file constructor that takes a
uh a a path a subpath as a a part of the
the constructor and goes and sticks in
the the separator for you. So we didn't
even need to call our function. It just
went and refactored it in the way that
that we expect uh we didn't even think
of. And I was just super impressed by
what what Juny can do. Um and so yeah,
if you're using uh any Jet Brains tool,
take advantage of Juny. It's it's a
really really handy tool and can can
help
you get going quickly. Um, so I have
gone a little bit over my time, but uh
I'm I'm open for any questions or any
any other comments people have.
Thank you so much. Uh, Scott, uh, that
was, um, I think everybody probably, uh,
their heart, uh, skipped a beat when you
showed that
graph. Uh, where are we going here? But
uh very insightful nonetheless. Yeah,
that's a scary thing. So, holy cow.
You'd think Gemini would be better.
Yikes. Actually, I'm just going to take
a screenshot of this because this is
this is going down the history books
right now.
Um and and just just uh for visibility,
we are sharing some of the very cool
insights um from the talk and this one
is definitely one of the controversial
ones. So, thank you, Scott. Okay.
Now um uh just wanted to say that yeah
we are getting closer to the end uh of
of our time here with this but extremely
extremely interesting uh topic. Uh there
is a lot of merit in saying that this is
probably one of the biggest areas right
now like refactoring legacy code. I
think if we don't uh nail this uh
anything else that's being built is
probably going to be uh obsolete. So,
and and and absolutely useless. So,
that's how you get a hold of me if you
need to. Yeah, exactly. Um, yeah. So,
just wanted to say thank you on behalf
of everyone in the community. I see that
the community has been super active, so
I think everyone really enjoyed the
talk. So, thank you so much, Scott.
Excellent. And I'm glad you liked it.